Guide to the Lev Lunts Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lev Lunt︠s︡ papers
1896-1931
GEN MSS 104
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.5
(5 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence of Lunt︠s︡ and his father, Natan Lunt︠s︡, writings, and personal papers of Lev and Natan Lunt︠s︡.
Lunt︠s︡, Lev, 1901-1924
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Lev Lunts Papers were purchased by Yale University in 1965 from Lunts's sister, Mrs. Genia Hornstein. The papers were discovered at Mrs. Hornstein's home in London in 1964 by Gary Kern. Mr. Kern identified the material and made the initial sorting.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers in box 5 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
LEV LUNTS (1901-1924)
Lev Natanovich Lunts, the promising but short-lived playwright, critic, and author, was born in St. Petersburg on May 2, 1901 (April 19, old style), into a family of Jewish intelligentsia. His father, Natan IAkovlevich, was a provisor and importer of optical instruments; his mother, Anna Efimovna, had been a concert pianist. He graduated from the St. Petersburg gimnasiia (high school) in 1918, with honors, and enrolled in the department of Romano-Germanic Languages and Literatures of the St. Petersburg University, where he studied under professors Dmitrii Petrov, Georgii Lozinskii, and others. He was considered an outstanding student and, upon graduation in 1922, was asked to remain on the faculty of his department as a post-graduate fellow. He began publishing his first articles of literary criticism in the St. Petersburg periodical ZHizn' Iskusstva in 1919-20.
While at the university, Lunts also attended lectures at "Dom Iskusstv," which was organized as part of Maksim Gorky's project, "Vsemirnaia Literatura," for the encouragement of young writers and poets, and which served from 1920 to 1923 as a place for meetings and lectures, and as a residence. The lectures and seminars there inspired him and his friend Mikhail Slonimskii, on the advice of Victor SHklovskii, to found the literary group known as "Serapionovy brat'ia" (Serapion Brothers). Its first meeting took place on February 1, 1921 in Slonimskii's room at Dom Iskusstv, where it continued to meet in its first years. Those present were: Il'ia Gruzdev, Veniamin Kaverin, Lev Lunts, Nikolai Nikitin, Elizaveta Polonskaia, Vladimir Pozner, Victor SHklovskii, Mikhail Slonimskii, and Mikhail Zoshchenko. Konstantin Fedin, Vsevolod Ivanov, and Nikolai Tikhonov joined the group that spring. Others who attended the meetings were the "Serapion maidens"-- Musia Alonkina, Zoia Gatskevich (Nikitina), Ida Kaplan, and Lidiia KHariton, as well as "guests," who included Evgenii Zamiatin, Olga Forsh, IUrii Tynianov, Anna Akhmatova, and Osip Mandel'shtam. The group was characterized by a deliberate lack of a single literary or ideological tendency and a common belief that the artistic claims of literature should not be subjugated to social agenda or political ideology. Lunts belonged to the left, "westernizing" wing of the Serapions, as he indicated in his article "O rodnykh brat'iakh" and the speech "Na zapad!", which was published in the Berlin periodical Beseda (number 3, 1923). The group came under attack by Marxist critics who accused its members of being "apolitical." Lunts responded to these criticisms in his articles "Pis'mo v redaktsiiu" and "Ob ideologii i publitsistike."
In June of 1921 Lev Lunts joined the All-Russian Professional Writers Union. In the same summer, his parents left Russia and moved to Germany. Lunts remained in St. Petersburg to finish his studies at the university. During the years 1921-23 he lived in the "obez'iannik" at Dom Iskusstv, along with other young writers, artists, and poets including Aleksandr Grin and Vladimir Piast. It was then that Lunts wrote and published the greater part of his works. By the end of 1922, beginning of 1923, he became known in St. Petersburg for his literary criticism, his plays Vne zakona and Bertrand-de-Born, and his controversial polemical articles "Pochemu my serapionovy brat'ia," and "Na zapad!".
In 1922 Lunts's health began to deteriorate. From his correspondence with his parents we learn that he originally decided to remain in Russia, although they repeatedly urged him to join them in Germany. By 1923, however, he was making every effort to obtain permission to travel abroad. With the help of Maksim Gorky, he procured an academic leave from the university and an exit visa for a literary-research trip to Spain. He left Russia on June 1, 1923. By the time he reached his parents in Hamburg, he was too sick to continue and went instead to a sanatorium in Koenigstein. It is there that he wrote the chronicle "Puteshestvie na bol'nichnoi koike." Lunts spent the last year of his life in sanatoriums and hospitals in Germany. For most of this time he was bedridden, at times partially paralyzed; at one point, after what was probably a stroke, he lost the ability to read and write and was obliged to teach himself again. Among his writings from this period was the second of his two screenplays, Vosstanie veshchei, and the play Gorod pravdy, which he sent to the Serapions. Lev Lunts died in the hospital in Eppendorf on May 9, 1924 at the age of 23. Bibliography Lunts, Lev. Rodina i drugie proizvedeniia. Ed. with an afterword and commentary by M. Vainshtein. Jerusalem: Pamiat', 1981. ---. Zaveshchanie TSaria. Ed. with an introduction by W. Schriek. Munich: Sagner, 1983. Novyi zhurnal. Number 79, New York, 1965: 44-79; Number 82, 1966: 136-92; Number 83, 1966: 132-84; Number 90, 1968: 39-57.
Scope and Contents
The Lev Lunts Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and personal papers that document the short career of the Russian playwright. Most papers date from between 1922 and 1930, but the collection spans the years 1896-1931. Except where indicated, all the papers are in Russian.
The papers are divided into three series; Correspondence (Box 1), Writings (Box 2-3), and Family Papers (Box 4), plus on box of Restricted Fragile Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, consists primarily of letters to Lev Lunts, some letters and drafts of letters written by him, and the personal correspondence of his father, Natan Lunts. Lev's correspondence covers two periods in his life. The first is the year after his parents' departure from Russia in the summer of 1921. This period is documented in the letters of Natan Lunts to Lev and in Lev's letters to his family, which are filed with the Outgoing correspondence. The second period is from June 1923 to May 1924, from the time that Lev left Russia and joined his parents until his death. In the last year of his life, Lunts corresponded actively with people in Russia, as well as friends from St. Petersburg who were already abroad. The correspondence of Natan Lunts dates, for the most part, from after Lev's death.
Among the items in the Incoming correspondence are letters from prominent literary figures such as Kornei Chukovskii, Maksim Gorky, Il'ia Erenburg, and Evgenii Zamiatin, as well as a number of letters from Nina Berberova, who befriended Lunts when he lived at Dom Iskusstv. Berberova writes from Berlin, then Marienbad, and finally from Venice, where she and Vladislav KHodasevich stopped briefly before moving to Paris. For the most part, these are letters of friendship and concern, but they deal also with literary issues, such as plans for the production of the German translation of Vne zakona in Berlin, and the publishing of Lunts's articles and other works in Beseda.
Other incoming letters are from Lunts's colleagues and personal friends, the fellow members of the Serapion Brothers. Most extensive are the correspondences of Lidiia KHariton and Ida Kaplan, two of the Serapion maidens, and of Vladimir Pozner, who was one of the first and youngest members of the group, but who had by this time emigrated to Paris with his parents. The correspondents relate the news of the group and its members and comment on their latest work. Another subject is Lunts's work, the publication and production of his writings and plays in Russia, including the fate of Vne zakona, and an account (L. KHariton) of the reactions of the Serapions to the play Gorod pravdy. These, and the letters from other Serapions, provide an insight into the spirit of youthful friendship in the group, the members' relationships to each other, and the characters of these young writers, who were later to have very different fates, some adjusting and becoming mainstream Soviet writers, some repressed, and some exiled. Taken together, these letters tell the story of a year in the life of the Serapion Brothers--their literary successes and failures and the developments in their personal lives, all against the background of the extraordinary historical events of the time. Also of note are a letter from Elizaveta Polonskaia with an autograph poem and one from Aleksandr Slonimskii, written collaboratively with Samuil Marshak, containing a humorous poem composed by the two. Some of these letters have been published in various issues of Novyi ZHurnal and in the collection Zaveshchanie TSaria. Also part of the Incoming correspondence are letters from Dmitrii Umanskii, Lunts's German translator, which discuss his work on Vne zakona, and his attempts to get it published and produced in German.
Most of the outgoing letters are written by Lev Lunts to his parents in the years 1922-23. He discusses his university studies, his literary success, his material circumstances, and, in the later letters, his health and his plans to leave Russia. There are also two letters to his sister Evgeniia; a draft of a letter to Gorky, in which he expresses despair at being chronically ill in the prime of his life and talks about the Serapions and his play Gorod pravdy, and a draft of a letter to Nikolai Nikitin and his wife Zoia, which is a humorous response to their letters of September 25, 1923 (Box 1, folder 17).
The correspondence of Natan Lunts is filed under its own heading. After Lev's death, his father kept in touch with some of his friends, including Nina Berberova, Ida Kaplan, Lidiia KHariton, Elizaveta Polonskaia, and Mikhail Slonimskii. At first his father and his friends share the pain and shock of their loss; later they discuss the care of his possessions, his manuscripts, and the plans (never materialized) by the Serapions to put out a two volume edition of Lunts's works, including some articles and obituaries by his friends. Also included is Natan's correspondence with translators Dmitrii Umanskii (German) and F. O. Dempsey (pseudonym, John Silver, English) regarding the publication and production of Lev's plays and Natan's personal correspondence with friends and relatives, including R. Jakobson and M. IArblum. The series concludes with three folders of condolence letters, telegrams, and cards to the family.
Series II, Writings is divided into four sections: Drama, Screenplays, Articles, and Shorter Works. Translations comprise a significant portion of this series. Items of particular interest are holograph originals of the unpublished screenplay Zaveshchanie TSaria; the humorous short story "KHozhdeniia", a parody of the Serapions which Lunts sent to them to be read at the group's anniversary celebration and which incited much commentary in the correspondence; and the chronicle "Puteshestvie na bol'nichnoi koike." Other holograph originals include a first draft of the play Gorod pravdy and a draft of the article "O rodnykh brat'iakh."
The third and final series, Family Papers, contains documents such as a birth certificate, educational and identification records; documents related to Lev Lunts's death and burial; and newspaper clippings with obituaries and posthumous articles by his friends, including Konstantin Fedin, Nina Berberova, and Mikhail Slonimskii. Other items include photographs of Lev, Ida Kaplan, and others; Lunts's wallet and its contents; and some newspaper clippings. One clipping, a short resolution, signed collectively by the Serapion Brothers and published in Leningradskaia Pravda on January 27, 1924, became the cause of the group's break with Nikolai Nikitin (see also Lidiia KHariton's letter of March 2, 1924). Also found in the series are some personal papers of Natan Lunts.
Authors, Russian -- 20th Century; Dramatists, Russian -- 20th Century; Russian drama -- 20th Century; Russian literature -- 20th Century; Sanatoriums -- Germany; Soviet Union -- History -- 1917-1936; Soviet Union -- Intellectual life -- 1917-1970; Dramatists; Berberova, N. (Nina), 1901-1993; Chukovskiĭ, Korneĭ, 1882-1969; Ėrenburg, Ilʹi︠a︡, 1891-1967; Fedin, Konstantin, 1892-1977; Kaplan, Ida; Kaverin, V. (Veniamin), 1902-1989; KHariton, Lidiia, 1899-; Lozinskii, Grigorii, 1886-1955; Lunt︠s︡, Lev, 1901-1924; Lunt︠s︡, Natan; Nikitin, Nikolaĭ, 1897-1963; Petrov, D. K(Dmitrĭ Konstantinovich), 1872-1925; Polonskai︠a︡, Elizaveta Grigorévna, 1890-; Pozner, Vladimir, 1905-1992; Shklovskiĭ, Viktor, 1893-1984; Slonimiskiĭ, Mikhail Leonidovich, 1897-1972; Slonimskiĭ, A. L(Aleksandr Leonidovich), 1884-1964; Tikhonov, Nikolaĭ, 1896-1979; Umanskii, Dmitrii; Zami͡atin, Evgeniĭ Ivanovich, 1884-1937
- Correspondence, 1922-31; Series I; 0.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence is divided into three alphabetically arranged subseries: Incoming, Outgoing, and Natan Lunts. The third subseries contains the incoming and outgoing correspondence of the Natan Lunts. Unidentified correspondence has been placed at the end of each subseries.
  - INCOMING
    - Alekseev, Gleb, 1923 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Berberova, Nina, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chukovskii, Kornei, 1924 Jan 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chukovskii, Nikolai (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Erenburg, Il'ia, 1923 Jul 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Fedin, Konstantin, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Lidiia KHariton, Box 1, folder 11
      See also: Serapion Brothers, Box 1, folder 21
    - Gorky, Maksim, 1923 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Gruzdev, Il'ia
      See: Serapion Brothers, Box 1, folder 21
    - Gurvich, Boris, 1924 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kaplan, Ida, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Kaplun, S., 1923 Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      See also: Dmitrii Umanskii, Box 1, folder 29
    - Kaverin, Veniamin, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - KHariton, Lidiia, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - Lozinskii, Grigorii, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lunts, Evgeniia, 1923 Sep 30, n.d (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lunts, Natan, 1922-23 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Marshak, Samuil
      See: Aleksandr Slonimskii, Box 1, folder 23
    - Nikitin, Nikolai, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Nikitina, Zoia, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Peshkov, Aleksei
      See: Maksim Gorky, Box 1, folder 6
    - Petrov, Dmitrii, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Polonskaia, Elizaveta, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Pozner, Vladimir, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Serapion Brothers, 1924 Feb 2, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - SHklovskii, Victor
    - SHvarts, Evgenii
      See: Ida Kaplan, Serapion Brothers, Box 1, folder 8
    - Slonimskaia, Faina, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      See also: Nikolai Slonimskii, Box 1, folder 25
    - Slonimskii, Aleksandr, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Slonimskii, Mikhail, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Slonimskii, Nikolai, [1923] (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Theaterverlag Otto Eirich (German), 1923 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Tikhonov, Nikolai, 1924 Feb 2, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Tynianov, IUrii, 1924 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Umanskii, Dmitrii, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
    - Vygodskii, David, 1923 Sep 27 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Zamiatina, Liudmila, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Zelënaia, Ekaterina
      See: Lidiia KHariton, Box 1, folder 11
    - Zoshchenko, Mikhail
    - Unidentified, 1924, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - OUTGOING
    - Gorky, Maksim, 1923 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Lunts, Evgeniia, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Lunts, Anna and Natan, 1922-23 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
    - Nikitin, Nikolai, 1923 Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Nikitina Zoia (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - NATAN LUNTS
    - Berberova, Nina, 1923, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Dempsey, F. O. (English), 1930 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      See also: Box 2, folders 72, 79-80
    - Grinberg, Roman, 1926 Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Jakobson, Roman, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - IArblum, M., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Kaplan, Ida, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Kaplun, S., 1924 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Kaverin, Veniamin, 1923 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - KHariton, Lidiia, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Levy, Felix, 1931 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Lunts, Anna, Evgeniia, Lev, 1923 Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Lurie (English), 1924 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Polonskaia, Elizaveta, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Silver, John
      See: F. O. Dempsey, Box 2, folder 41
    - Slonimskii, Mikhail, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Umanskii, Dmitrii, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Unidentified, 1923-25, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Condolence letters (Russian, German, English, Yiddish), 1924 (Box 1, Folder 56-58)
- Writings, 1922-30; Series II; 0.75; (2 boxes)
  The writings are divided into four subseries: Drama, Screenplays, Articles, and Shorter Works. Within each subseries, the papers are arranged alphabetically by title and then in the following order: holographs, typescripts, printed versions, publication/production notices, publicity, reviews, and then translations in the same order.
  - DRAMA
    - Bertrand-de-Born
      - Typescript, carbon, 1922 Sep 14 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      - Printed, proof, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Gorod pravdy
      - Holograph, first draft, corrected, bound with "KHozhdeniia" and "O rodnykh brat'iakh" (Box 2, Folder 61)
      - Holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - Typescript, carbons, entitled Kontsa net, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 63-65)
      - Review, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - City of Truth (English tr. by John Silver)
        - Typescript, carbon, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 67)
        - Printed, first edition, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 68)
        - Publication notices, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 69-71)
        - Rejection notices from theaters, 1929-30 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      - Die Stadt der Gleichheit (German tr. by Erich Bohme)
        - Typescript, original, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Obez'iany idut!
      - Printed, proof, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Vne zakona
      - Printed, proof, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 75)
      - Production announcement, annotated, 1924 Jun 8 (Box 2, Folder 76)
      - Outside the Law (English tr. by John Silver)
        - Typescript, carbon, with holograph coverletter by translator, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 77)
        - Typescript, carbon, bound, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 78)
        - Rejection notice from publisher, 1930 Jan 10 (Box 2, Folder 79)
        - Rejection notices from theaters, 1929-30 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Vogelfrei (German)
      - Printed, in Der Querschnitt, 1925 Jan (Box 2, Folder 81)
      - Theater program, 1926 Dec 4 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - SCREENPLAYS
    - Vosstanie veshchei
      - Holograph, draft I, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 83)
      - Holograph, draft II, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Zaveshchanie TSaria
      - Holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - ARTICLES
    - "Das Herbende russiche Theater": printed, newspaper clipping (German), 1924 Aug 10 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - "Na zapad!": printed, proofs, two copies, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 87)
      - Publicity (photocopies), 1923-24 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - "O rodnykh brat'iakh": holograph draft, n.d.
      See: Gorod pravdy, Box 2, folder 61
  - SHORTER WORKS
    - "KHozhdeniia": holograph, draft, n.d.
    - "Puteshestvie na bol'nichnoi koike": holograph, draft, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 89)
- Family Papers, 1896-1927; Series III; 0.5; (1 box)
  These materials are divided into two subseries: Biographical Materials, and Other papers and effects. This last is further divided under two headings: Lev Lunts, and Natan Lunts. Within these, papers are arranged alphabetically by subject. Miscellaneous papers and empty envelopes are placed at the end of the series.
  - BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
    - Birth certificate, 1902 Oct 21 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Death and burial documents, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 91-92)
    - Death notices (photocopies), 1924 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Educational records, 1918-23 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Medical bills, receipts, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Obituaries, necrologies (photocopies), 1924 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Vital records (passport, etc.), 1921-23 (Box 4, Folder 97-98)
  - OTHER PAPERS AND EFFECTS
    - Lev Lunts
      - Newspaper clippings, 1924-27 (Box 4, Folder 99)
      - Photographs, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 100)
      - Wallet and contents (miscellaneous papers, currency, stamps) (Box 4, Folder 101-04)
    - Natan Lunts
      - Diploma, 1895 Dec 20 (Box 4, Folder 105)
      - Newspaper article by N. Lunts (German), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 106)
      - Newspaper clippings (Russian, Hebrew, Yiddish), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 107-08)
      - Miscellaneous papers, n.d (Box 4, Folder 109-11)
      - Empty envelopes, 1924-30, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 112)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted Fragile Papers in box 5 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
  - Box 2, folder 66 (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - Box 3, folder 89 (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Box 4, folder 94 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Box 4, folder 97 (Box 5, Folder 116)